<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Great news from Falmouth, or, A true and impartial account of a bloody fight between the tinners of Cornwall and the Kings forces in the town of Falmouth on Tuesday and Wednesday, the 27th and 28th of May in a letter from Falmouth.</title>
            <author>T. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C134</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12097571</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12097571</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 57:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Great news from Falmouth, or, A true and impartial account of a bloody fight between the tinners of Cornwall and the Kings forces in the town of Falmouth on Tuesday and Wednesday, the 27th and 28th of May in a letter from Falmouth.</title>
                  <author>T. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Timothy Johnson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: T.C.</note>
                  <note>"Licens'd and entred according to order"</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army.</term>
               <term>Falmouth (England) --  Riot, 1690.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54003:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Great News from FALMOUTH, OR, A True and Impartial ACCOUNT, OF A Bloody FIGHT Between the Tinners of Cornwall, And the Kings Forces in the Town of Falmouth; On <hi>Tueſday</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> the <hi>27th.</hi> and <hi>28th.</hi> of <hi>May.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In a LETTER from <hi>FALMO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Licens'd and Entred according to Order.</p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ON <hi>Tueſday</hi> and <hi>Yeſterday</hi> there was an extraordinary Riot in this Town, as followeth: A falſe Report was ſpread about the Country, that the <hi>French</hi> Goods on Board ſeveral Prices in this Port were to be Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Whereupon the <hi>Tinners</hi> and Country Rabble, to the Number of Three or Four Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, came into the Town, and went directly to the Key, Swearing that the <hi>Salt</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Goods which they wonted ſo much, ſhould not be thrown into the Sea, but that they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54003:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> would have it; the Officers of the Cuſtoms Interpoſed, and told them the Hazard of the Enterpriſe they were going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, to break up thoſe Ships whoſe Hatches were Locked and Sealed, and the Ships and Goods the Kings. And to Pacify them, told them (what was never intended to be Perform'd) that when the ſaid Gooods were Condemned, and to be Deſtroyed, they ſhould have a Publick and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Notice of it, wherewith they were well ſattisfied; and going off. When ſeveral of the Townſmen called them Fools, and Eged them on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; whereupon, they En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and brok up the firſt Ship they come at, Laden chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>Salt,</hi> which they Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loded by the begining of the Night, and then gave over till the Morning; by which time their Number were Increaſed to near Two Thouſand in all, Men and Women: The Men Declared for <hi>Salt, Wine,</hi> and <hi>Brandy;</hi> and the Women De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for <hi>Linnen,</hi> Reſolving to Plunder every Ship in the Port.</p>
            <p>The Captain of <hi>Pendenis</hi> ſent down (at the Requeſt of the Price Officers) Two Files of Muſqueteers to help Guard the next Ship they were to come at: Which they Entererd not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, and Aſſaulting the Souldiers, forced ſome of them to make uſe of Ball, who ſhot only with Powder before, ſo that one of the Ring-Leaders was ſhot through the Body, another in the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, a third had his Belly ſlit up with a Baggonet, that his Bowels hung out, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others Pricked and Wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>But this had not Ended, but Encreaſed the Miſchief, if they had not bethought themſelves of ſomge reat Guns that were on Board, which they Mounted and Loaded preſently in the View of the whole Rout, and Runing with Lighted Matches as if they would have immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately Fired amongſt them; the Women began to ſhriek out and Fly! and the Men by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees followed them, till they all got out of Town.</p>
            <p>So that we are now quite rid of them, being quietly gon to their Reſpective Habitations of this Town. Many Joined with them, whom I ſuppoſe the Officers of the Cuſtoms will take Care to Proſecute.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Falmouth, <date>May the 29th. 1690</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>I am <hi>Sir,</hi>
               </salute>
               <signed>Your Servant, <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> Timothy Johnſon, <hi>at</hi> Charing-Croſs. 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
